When we think of German rail, we imagine
the pinnacle of rail transport, the best
trains and tracks ever, a system so
punctual you can set your watch to it,
an industry leader carrying the torch of
European rail. This idea is so
entrenched in our culture that even the
Big Bang Theory included it in a scene
where Sheldon is like
>> My bowel movements run like a German
train schedule.
>> But you may or may not be surprised to
learn that this is not how Germans think
of German rail, or anyone else who has
used it more than once. Because, and it
pains me to say this, but German rail is
utter [__]
Train cancellations, breakdowns, delays,
decaying infrastructure, filthy
stations, utter chaos, Weichenstörung,
the AC doesn't work, the toilet is
clogged, and you're trying to get on,
but someone walled off the [__] door.
Meanwhile, punctuality in long-distance
traffic is reaching historic lows,
currently hovering around 60% in late
2025, going as low as 51.5%.
Leonard, my bowel movements run like a
German train schedule. I haven't been on
the toilet for 5 days. It can come at
any moment. I have no idea when.
Leonard, help me. I can't leave the
house. I'm trapped.
As of 2026, German rail is in shambles.
Now, some people might butt in and say
that this is still better than in my
country. Yeah, great. Where do you live?
Albania. Yeah, of course it's better,
but everything is relative. Like imagine
your tap water being slightly yellow and
smelling funny. It's nothing dangerous,
but you still complain about it. But
then some genius comes along and says,
"Well, did you know that some people in
Central Africa don't even have running
water in their house?" Yeah, great, but
I'm not some people, and I don't live in
Central Africa. I live in a developed
country. I pay taxes, [music] lots of
taxes. I pay my bills, and so I want
clean water in my [__] tap as a
civilizational minimum. Same thing with
[music] rail. Actually, it's worse,
considering that Germany is Europe's
biggest and strongest economy. You're
the richest and most powerful, and this
is what you were able to accomplish? 60%
punctuality, rotting infrastructure,
aging rolling stock, filthy stations.
That's [music] it? Mediocre. And it's
all because of politics. To understand
what the issue is, picture your average
aging post-war centrist politician. They
don't believe in much. They don't have
any particular strong beliefs about
anything. They have no particular
ideology or vision. The only thing they
are able or willing to do is to keep the
system going somehow. To be fair, for
most of their lives, they've been living
in a world where that's all they had to
do. Pax Americana, the Soviet Union was
done, Western neoliberal capitalism
reigned supreme globally, and so [music]
on. So really, all they had to do was to
keep the machine running. And back then,
it really looked like their world will
be the end all, be all. New modern
technology started appearing, like
airplanes that weren't dangerous, or
cars that would reliably start in the
morning. Look at that sleek modern bus,
that car, that sleek modern airplane.
How cool they are, how new they are. Now
compare them to the old and busted
trains and trams chugging on rails from
the previous century. Obviously, the
future is roads, airports, cars, and
airplanes. Maybe buses. And once again,
in their defense, back then, it really
looked like that's going to be the
future. Wait, what's that? Japan built
high-speed rail, proving that rail is
actually the future of long-distance
transport? Ah, we're just going to
ignore that. But such politicians in
Europe couldn't just rip up all their
tracks and kill rail transport like
Americans did. Voters in Europe would
not have liked that. So instead, they
just started defunding and neglecting
rail. Except for a few important lines
that served as a showcase kind of,
[music] around which the entire system
was slowly decaying. But hey, oh my god,
look at this shiny new train, the
Intercity Express. [music] It's
basically an airplane on tracks.
Seriously, things start making so much
sense once you realize that those
post-war boomer politicians could only
think in terms of airplanes and cars. So
when designers showed them the ICE 1's
interior, they were like, "Hmm, I'm
getting I'm getting airplane vibes from
this. Great, approved." So while the
post-war political class labored on
making rail service look and feel more
like airplanes and or luxury cars, the
only things they ever knew, the rest of
the system was slowly decaying. Switches
and side tracks were removed because
they were not efficient enough. So,
let's just rip them up. We save on
maintenance and so rail will make a
profit. Everything has to make a profit.
It's the 1990s. The name of the game is
generic skyscrapers, airplanes, cars,
and the line going up. Imagine like an
endless vaporwave music video,
basically. That's the world they wanted.
But then, one little global oil shock
later, we started realizing that trains
were actually pretty great. In fact,
when built properly, they are superior
to cars and airplanes. If only someone
had proven this already. So, all right.
German rail starts investing in rolling
stock. The Deutschlandticket comes out,
providing unlimited countrywide train
travel at a bargain price. People flock
to rail. Passenger numbers are at
constant growth. And then, the cracks
start appearing. As traffic volume
grows, punctuality and reliability take
a nose dive. Mostly in long-distance
traffic. Local traffic is still fine by
and large, though only due to shorter
distances and the sheer volume of
transit. Long-distance rail, though, is
screwed, producing the aforementioned
bottom-of-the-barrel lows of 51.5%
punctuality, with trains being, quote
unquote, punctual as long as their delay
does not exceed 6 minutes. So, what went
wrong? Why is this happening? The short
answer, because they took all those new
traffic volumes and threw them on a
decrepit, underfunded, crumbling
network, which was meant for half that
volume back in 1965
when it was still new. It's hard to
maintain a constant and frequent service
of long-distance, local, and freight
services on tracks built half a century
ago with most of the equipment being
decades past its original intended
service life. Because of that, you get
things like what happened with the
Deutschlandtakt, an integrated [music]
clockface schedule timetable for the
entire country. If you don't know what
that does, basically, it makes all the
trains be very punctual, the schedule
very reliable, and rail travel very
convenient. Everything is connected to
everything. Frequencies are high.
Everything is on time. It's what the
Swiss have. And their punctuality is the
best in Europe at 94.1%
and for them a punctual train is one
with less than 3 minutes of delay, not
six like Deutsche Bahn. Hey, do you know
what else is Swiss? ProtonMail, the
sponsor of today's video. Are you
looking to break free from American Big
Tech to not have all your data flow
through the computers of Silicon Valley
tech oligarchs? Well, now here's
ProtonMail to the rescue. ProtonMail is
a privacy-focused encrypted email
service keeping your personal data safe.
Not even Proton can see what's in your
emails as opposed to services like Gmail
where your emails may or may not be used
to train AI. ProtonMail is funded
entirely by its user base meaning they
have no incentive to sell off your data
to third parties. Migrating from Gmail
is easy. It takes 30 seconds to move
everything from your old account. If you
want to keep your old Gmail, that's not
an issue at all. With easy switch you
can have your mail forwarded to your new
Proton account automatically. Proton is
also a European provider. Therefore, as
I've mentioned, it's an alternative to
Silicon Valley big tech oligarchs and
their increasingly predatory services.
Go to proton.me/adamsomething
to get started with ProtonMail for free.
Their service is always free with
optional paid plans for additional
features and benefits. That's
proton.me/adamsomething.
Thank you for checking out ProtonMail.
So, the Deutschlandtakt was envisioned
for Germany as a way to create a
world-class rail system rivaling that of
Switzerland. Plans were to enact it in
2030, but because of the state of German
rail infrastructure, it had to be
postponed a little bit by 40 [__]
years. Deutschlandtakt [music]
coming in 2070 brought to you by the
country with Europe's strongest economy.
Because of the constant problems with
German rail, Swiss railways actually
started restricting the entry of German
trains. The rule is if an ICE is late,
it does not go further than the first
station past the border. From there,
passengers are free to use local Swiss
railways trains to their destinations.
Because German rail is so unreliable, it
actually started messing with the
meticulously designed Swiss train
schedule, which is beyond embarrassing
of course. When your rail system is so
[__] that your neighbors stop letting in
your trains. Speaking of,
Now, when we think of German rail, we
usually think of rail within Germany.
Now, you could say, well, duh, it's
German rail. Uh, but it's not that
simple. Austrian rail, OBB, has an
impressive international network. Their
trains go everywhere, even to Italy,
despite the fact that, as they say, it's
easier to send a train to the moon and
then to Italy. German rail is much
bigger than Austrian rail. They have
more and more diverse rolling stock, a
larger network, more employees, and they
are strategically situated in the very
center of Europe, directly bordering
nine countries. Historically, Germany
has had a large international network,
including via the Trans Europ Express
program. Now, that was first class only,
sort of a rare premium service, but the
TEE network and the trains were the
precursors for things like the ICE, TGV,
Railjet, and so on. When the TEE network
began shrinking, it did so because its
lines were replaced by more frequent
services that also included things like
second class. [music] Now, back during
the '70s and '80s, you could just get on
an international train in Berlin and
travel as far as Bucharest in Romania.
Oh, no, no, no, no, not this again.
So, yeah, German international rail has
historically been pretty great. So, what
does it look like today? How does the
richest and most powerful country in
Europe with the largest rail network
handle its international passenger rail
after the fall of the Berlin Wall, open
internal borders, no border checks in
the Schengen era of free movement? Well,
here is the long-distance rail network
of Germany, a very impressive system,
despite the German political elite's
best efforts. Now, let's see their
international connections.
Yeah. Ah, but wait, let's also delete
seasonal and very infrequent lines.
There we go. Three or less trains per
day per direction is not a real rail
service, after all. It's a Disneyland
ride for people who chose the train path
on their autism tech tree, like I did.
Ah, but let's be even more precise here
and include only those international
connections run by German rail's own
rolling stock. There we go, Deutsche
Bahn, yeah. [music] These scant few
international connections running
through this country in the very center
of Europe are mostly run by other
countries. Connections towards Poland
are run by PKP Intercity, Denmark runs
its own fleet of Talgo trains running as
DSB Eurocities. To Czechia, it's
officially a cooperation between České
dráhy, Czech Railways, and Deutsche
Bahn, which consisted of DB slapping a
sticker on the side of each car. And
then Deutsche Bahn started [__] with
České dráhy, stopping trains on the
border, not letting them into the
country because of some alleged minor
technical defects on some of the cars.
What those three to 400 passengers will
do on the border during a summer
heatwave with the next already
overloaded train coming in 2 hours only?
Well, that sounds like a Czech Railways
problem.
Hungarian Railways also runs trains on
this route between Budapest and Hamburg.
Hey everyone, just jumping in here
during the editing process with a quick
correction. Hungaria trains are no
longer run using Hungarian Railways
rolling stock as of December 2025. Czech
Railways took over fully with a brand
new Railjet sets, and thank god for
that. My condolences to all those who
got scoliosis from those goddamn seats.
Their rolling stock is [__] but hey, at
least it's there. Hungarian Railways
actually eats losses on this line, but
they do it anyway as public service.
This being essentially a favor to
Deutsche Bahn. And then Deutsche Bahn
started [__] with them, too. Having
discovered a technical defect at the
border, they once again barred it from
entering. So, dear hundreds of
passengers, get the hell out onto the
platform because one of the cars had a
non-functional AC, and one of the
windows had its upper part slightly
broken. Well, should they just, I don't
know, empty out that one car and lock it
down? No. Let's just terminate the
entire [__] train because why not?
Things got so out of control, the Czech
Ministry of Transportation had to
intervene, officially asking Deutsche
Bahn to let the trains go at least until
Dresden, the first major German city on
the route, just on the other side of the
border. So, we don't have hundreds of
people milling around this small border
station causing chaos by trying to get
on the next already overloaded train.
So, Deutsche Bahn said, "Sure, fine.
Even if there's a problem, we let the
trains go on to Dresden. We won't stop
them on the border anymore. We promise."
And then they did it again anyway. But
hey, if you think that's bad, then may I
present to you the Prague-Munich
International Rail Line, brought to you
by the Free State of Bavaria. Actually,
you know what? Nah, [__] it. We're doing
this.
Bavaria is one of the richest regions in
Germany and in Europe. They are
Switzerland outside Switzerland. And
what do they do with their immense
wealth and prosperity? [music] Where do
they invest it? Not in the rail, I tell
you that much. If you want a picture of
Bavaria, you can get it like so. Imagine
a bunch of syrupy sweet bucolic
gingerbread houses on the Windows XP
background.
>> [music]
>> Add highways everywhere. Also, like two
cities that are basically enclaves of
young people as last desperate bastions
of actual living culture. Then throw a
bunch of fat disgusting boomers in giant
luxury cars everywhere. Then douse
everything with beer. Welcome to Bayern.
When I first traveled through Bavaria by
train, I was very surprised. Not in a
good way. We have this region with
high-tech industry, a global leader with
incredible wealth and all. And
meanwhile, here I am slowly chugging
along a single track on electrified rail
line on a train built half a century
ago. As I look outside, I see a rich
boomer zooming past the eight-lane
perfectly flat concrete highway. It's
Markus Söder, the emperor of Bavaria,
sitting in a black BMW SUV larger than a
Panzer II. His ass fused to the leather
seat equipped with heating and cooling
and other technology that would have
been featured on Star Trek 30 years ago.
>> Take the easy way out, literally.
Go to the seat comfort app, find comfort
exit, and activate it. Switch off the
driving ready state, unfasten, and enjoy
your seat automatically moving back for
a comfortable [music] exit.
>> All the while, Bavarian rail is going to
[__] even more so than the rest of the
country. But hey, at least those BMW
cars are very comfortable. Oh wait,
what's this? Oh my god, these people are
[__] stereotypes. And the single
track slow on electrified rail line in
question, the one that I took, is
actually the Prague-Munich international
mainline. What the [__] These people do
not give a [__] To check yes credit
here, they've been wanting to redo the
line for a long time, but they were
universally met with complete
disinterest from the German side.
>> Why do you want the rail line there?
There's a highway already.
>> Czechs are about to upgrade the line,
their half anyway. Electrification,
ETCS, 200 km/h, but because of Germany's
lack of interest, they won't add the
required capacity. Parts of the line
will be single track and the end section
will only receive a lesser overall.
Because why build this out fully if it
won't be used fully for the next 20
years? Because the capacity is missing
on the other side and will continue
doing so until members of the current
Bavarian political elite reach the
[music] end of their natural lifespans.
Anyway, that's Bavaria for you. German
rail as a whole though is not much
better, especially when Deutsche Bahn,
the German state and other giant
corporations start to collude.
A couple of years ago, German rail came
up with a wonderful idea. They applied
for and received funding for a
revolutionary new freight car brake
system, so-called LL blocks or whisper
brakes. The nice thing about them is
that they are very silent. They are
advanced, modern, great, good,
environmentally friendly, and it just
happens to be only produced by
Knorr-Bremse, a major German
corporation. So, step one, Germany asks
for and receives EU funding for new
train brakes which are only produced by
one German company. Step two,
the Gotthard Base Tunnel derailment,
causing 150 million euros worth of
damage and shutting down the most
important piece of Swiss rail
infrastructure for more than a year.
Brought to you by German federal level
corruption. The problem with the LL
blocks or whisper brakes is that they
overheat, leading to increased material
fatigue over time or even fires. But
hey, at least Knorr Bremse made a lot of
cash with them. Next to stuff like this,
others look like mere tiny details, like
Deutsche Bahn Cargo operating in open
violation of European law about
forbidden state aid for 20 years and
only now deciding that it's time to play
by the rules. Rules which Germany helped
draft and specifically agreed to.
>> [gasps]
>> What a [__] mess. And by the way, the
Deutschland ticket didn't even work that
well, even when it only cost €9 for
unlimited national public transit use.
Car traffic decreased only by 4 to 5%,
but train delays increased by 30%
because people didn't really change cars
for trains. They just started to take
the train more often on the rotting,
dilapidated rail system designed to deal
with half that load. [music] And that's
when [__] really started going downhill.
Now, as of late, Germany began to
invest, or rather reinvest into its rail
system. It kind of sort of started
crawling out of the pit, which is nice.
But to achieve lasting results, we need
someone else in charge. Up until
recently, Germany has been led by a
particularly uncharismatic Burger King
manager, but maybe even that [music]
would be beyond his leadership
capabilities. But now, instead of him,
we have an arrogant, snooty bank manager
with great popular and timely ideas such
as ending the German welfare state in
the middle of a cost of living crisis.
So, yeah, get ready for the fourth Reich
or something. And if you have the right
to vote, do vote for Die Linke or Die
Grünen, the left or the greens. You get
to avert the rise of Twitter fascism and
also get leaders who are able to view
the world in terms of actual public
transit, not just cars and airplanes.
Thank you for watching my tirade against
German Rail. If you like my content,
please consider supporting me on Patreon
or become a channel member here on
YouTube. I also have a tabletop
wargaming in the works. The link to our
playtesting Discord is in the
description as well. Thank you for
watching once again, and I'll be seeing
you next time.
>> [music]
>> Woo.
Woo.
>> [music]
>> Woo.
Woo.